Register of the Russia. Posol'stvo (U.S.) Records, 1897-1947.
Hoover Institution Archives
Russia. Posol'stvo (U.S.) Records
1897-1947
33005
Hoover Institution Archives
383 manuscript boxes, 85 oversize boxes, 6 card file boxes, 6 envelopes (240 linear feet)
Correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, reports, agreements, minutes, histories, financial records, lists, and printed matter, relating to Russia's role in World War I, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, activities of the Russian Red Cross, Russian emigres in foreign countries, and operations of the embassy office. Includes files of the Russian Military, Naval, and Financial Attaches in the United States; the Russian State Control Office and the Russian Supply Committee Office in the United States; and the Consulate General in Montreal, Canada. Entire collection also on microfilm (484 reels).
Russia. Posol'stvo (United States)
Access
Microfilm use only.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1933.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (484 reels).
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, reports, agreements, minutes, histories, financial records, lists, and printed matter, relating to Russia's role in World War I, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, activities of the Russian Red Cross, Russian emigres in foreign countries, and operations of the embassy office. Includes files of the Russian Military, Naval, and Financial Attaches in the United States; the Russian State Control Office and the Russian Supply Committee Office in the United States; and the Consulate General in Montreal, Canada. Entire collection also on microfilm (484 reels).
Historical Note
Russian Imperial and Provisional Government embassy in the United States.
Rossiiskoe obshchestvo krasnogo kresta..; Vooruzhennye Sily na IUgie Rossii.; Canada--Foreign relations--Russia.; Canada.; Russia--Foreign relations--Canada.; Russia--Foreign relations--United States.; Russia.; Russians in foreign countries.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Russia.; United States--Foreign relations.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918--War work.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Correspondence, 1915-1922.
  General note
  Available on microfilm reels 1-3
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General (Box 1)
    - 1915 (Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 1
    - 1917 (Folder 2)
    - 1917-1918
      - General (Folder 3)
      - Telegrams (Folder 4)
    - 1918 (Folder 5)
    - 1918-1919 (Folder 6)
    - 1919 (Box 2)
      - General
        - January-February (Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 2
        - March-April (Folder 2)
        - May-June (Folder 3)
        - June-December (Folder 4)
      - Letters (Folder 5)
      - Telegrams
        - January-August (Folder 6)
        - July-September (Box 3, Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 3
        - September-December (Folder 2)
    - 1919-1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1920 (Folder 2)
    - 1920-1921 (Folder 3)
    - 1921 (Folder 4)
    - 1922
      - General (Folder 5)
      - Letters (Folder 6)
  - Girs, Mikhail
    - 1920 (Folder 7)
    - 1921 (Folder 8)
    - 1922 (Folder 9)
  - Russian Foreign Ministry, Omsk, 1919 (Folder 10)
  - Sazonov, Sergei (see also Girs, Mikhail, 1920) (Folder 11)
- Subject File, 1897-1947.
  Available on microfilm reels 4-45
  Clippings, communiques, correspondence, financial records, memoranda, minutes, notes, printed matter, reports, speeches, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General (Box 5)
    - Clippings
      - 1917 (Folder 1)
        Available on microfilm reel 4
      - 1918 (Folder 2)
      - 1919
        - July (Folder 3)
        - October (Folder 4)
        - November (Folder 5)
        - November-December (Folder 6)
        - December (Folder 7)
      - 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      - 1920
        - January (Folder 3)
          Available on microfilm reel 5
        - January-March (Folder 4)
      - 1921 (Folder 5)
      - 1922 (Folder 6)
    - Financial records (Box 7)
      - 1917
        - Cashbooks (Folder 1-2)
        - Checkstubs (Folder 3)
      - 1917-1920 (Folder 4)
      - 1919 (Folder 5)
        Available on microfilm reel 6
      - 1920 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 1921 (Folder 2)
      - 1922 (Folder 3)
    - Printed matter
      - Booklets (Folder 4)
      - Periodicals
        - Bibliografia polska, Krakow
          - 1917 (Folder 5)
          - 1918 (Folder 6)
          - 1919 (Folder 7)
            Available on microfilm reel 7
        - Economic Statistical Bulletin, Budapest, 1947
          - Issues 2-4 (Folder 8)
          - Issues 5-6 (Folder 9)
  - Allied policies towards Russia. (see also Propaganda/Anti- communist) (Box 9)
    - 1918 (Folder 1)
    - 1919 (Folder 2)
    - 1920 (Folder 3)
    - 1921 (Folder 4)
    - 1922 (Folder 5)
  - American Federation of Labor--see Propaganda/Anti-communist
  - Bakhmet'ev, Boris--see Borah, William
  - Benes, Edward--see Russian intelligence service/1922/Russian Military Agent in Czechoslovakia
  - Borah, William. (see also Allied policies towards Russia/ 1922; and Semenov, Grigorii) (Folder 6)
  - Breshkovskaia, Ekaterina (Folder 7)
  - Bulgaria--see Slavs
  - China
    - 1918 (Folder 8)
    - 1920 (Folder 9)
  - Chinese Eastern Railway. (see also China)
  - Commerical products
    - 1919 (Folder 11)
    - 1920-1921 (Folder 12)
      Available on microfilm reel 8
  - Czechoslovakia--see Russian intelligence service/1921 and 1922
  - Eddystone Ammunition Company, Philadelphia (Folder 13)
  - European War, 1914-1918
    - Campaigns--see Subject File/Golovin, Nikolai, Lieutenant-General/Izlovetz battle, 1916
    - Russian prisoners of war (Folder 14)
  - Germonius, Eduard, Lieutenant-General (Folder 15)
  - Golovin, Nikolai, Lieutenant-General (Box 10)
    - General (Folder 1)
    - Academy of General Staff, Petrograd (Folder 2)
    - Awards and decorations (Folder 3-4)
    - Izlovetz battle, 1916 (Folder 5)
  - Hoover, Herbert--see Allied policies towards Russia/1922
  - Japan
    - 1919 (Folder 6)
    - 1920 (Folder 7)
      Available on microfilm reel 9
    - 1921 (Folder 8)
  - Kotliarevskii, H., Istoriia novoi russkoi literatury ot Gogolia do nashikh dnei, St. Petersburg, 1897 (Folder 9)
  - Kovalev, The Iron Industry of Russia, New York, 1919 (Folder 10)
  - Laskin, Boris (Folder 11)
  - Lenin, Vladimir--see Russia/General/1920 and 1921
  - Leont'ev, Major-General--see Russian intelligence service/ 1921-1922 and 1922/Russian Military Agent in Czechoslovakia
  - Lomonosov, Iurii--see Subagencies/Division of Supplies/ Mission of Ways of Communication
  - Makarov, L. N., Captain (Folder 12)
  - Martens, L.--representative of Soviet Russia in the United States, 1919 (Folder 13)
  - Novitskii, Vladimir--see Subagencies/Consulates/Savings banks
  - Paris, Conference of, 1919-1920 (Folder 14)
  - Pavlov, Mikhail (Folder 15)
  - Propaganda
    - Anti-communist
      - 1919 (Folder 16)
      - 1920 (Folder 17)
    - Communist--see Subject File/Russian intelligence service; and Subject File/Subagencies/Consulates/ General/1919/Left wing movements in North America
  - Refugees, Russian. (see also Russian missions and legations) (Box 11)
    - General
      - 1920 (Folder 1)
      - 1921
        - January-December (Folder 2)
        - June-September (Folder 3)
          Available on microfilm reel 10
      - 1921-1922 (Folder 4)
    - China (Folder 5)
    - Konstantinovs' affair (Folder 6)
  - North America (Box 12)
    - General
      - 1918
        - January-May (Folder 1)
        - June-August (Folder 2)
          Available on microfilm reel 11
        - September-November (Folder 3)
        - November-December (Folder 4)
      - 1919
        - January-April (Folder 5)
        - January-December (Folder 6)
        - 1919-1920 (Folder 7)
        - 1920-1921 (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - 1921 (Folder 2)
          Available on microfilm reel 12
        - 1921-1922 (Folder 3)
      - Veterans
        - General (Folder 4)
        - U.S. War Risk Insurance Bureau (Folder 5)
    - Organizations
      - General
        - 1921
          - January-October (Folder 6)
          - June-December (Folder 7)
        - 1921-1922 (Folder 8)
        - 1922 (Box 14, Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 13
      - All-Russian Constituent Assembly -- conference, Paris, 1921 (Folder 2)
      - American Central Committee for Russian Relief
        - 1920 (Folder 3)
        - 1921 (Folder 4)
        - 1922 (Folder 5)
      - American Committee of Siberian Agricultural Cooperative Unions--see Committee on Revival of Russia
      - Association of Russian Foreign Ministry Employees (Folder 6)
      - Bureau of Russian Press, Constantinople. Bulletins, 1920-1921 (Folder 7)
      - Committee on Revival of Russia (Folder 8)
      - Russian Aid Society
        - Advance payments
          - Receipts, 1921
            - September (Folder 9)
            - October (Folder 10)
            - November (Folder 11)
          - Reports (Folder 12)
        - Secret affair, 1921 (Folder 13)
          Available on microfilm reel 14
      - Russian Liberation Committee, London
        - 1919 (Folder 14)
        - 1920 (Folder 15)
      - Russian Red Cross. (see also American Central Committee for Russian Relief) (Box 15)
        - 1919 (Folder 1)
        - 1920 (Folder 2)
        - 1921 (Folder 3-4)
        - 1922 (Folder 5)
      - Russian Zemstvos and Cities Relief Committee
        - 1920 (Folder 6)
        - 1921 (Folder 7)
    - Relief. (see also Organizations)
      - General (Folder 8)
        Available on microfilm reel 15
      - Cherep-Spiridonovich, Major-General (Folder 9)
      - Shmidt, E. V. (Folder 10)
    - Serbia--see Turkey and Serbia
    - Turkey and Serbia. (see also Subject File/Slavs/ 1920) (Folder 11)
    - Veterans (Folder 12)
  - Russia (Box 16)
    - General
      - 1920 (Folder 1)
      - 1921
        - January-August (Folder 2)
        - January-December (Folder 3)
        - March-September (Folder 4)
          Available on microfilm reel 16
      - 1921-1922 (Folder 5)
      - 1922
        - March-April (Folder 6)
        - April-June (Folder 7)
    - Famine - American private relief organizations (Folder 8)
    - Ministry of Finance, 1916-1917 (Box 17)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Budget of Russian Empire, 1917
        - Part 1
          - in English (Folder 2)
          - in French (Folder 3)
            Available on microfilm reel 17
        - Part 2 (Folder 4)
    - Revolution, 1917-1921
      - Counterrevolutionary movements. (see also Subject File/Germonius, Eduard; Subject File/Russian Information Bureau; Subject File/Russian intelligence service; Subject File/Russian missions and legations; Subject File/Russian secret police)
        - Government and politics
          - Banknotes (Folder 5)
          - Far East. (see also Subject File/ Sub- agencies/Consulates/San Francisco/Far East; Subject File/Semenov, Grigorii)
            - 1918 (Folder 6)
            - 1921 (Folder 7)
            - 1922 (Folder 8)
          - North (Box 18)
            - 1918 (Folder 1)
            - 1919 (Folder 2)
            - 1920 (Folder 3)
          - Siberia. (see also Subject File/ Semenov, Grigorii)
            - General
              - 1919 (Folder 4)
                Available on microfilm reel 18
              - 1920 (Folder 5)
            - All-Russian Government, Omsk
              - General
                - Correspondence (Folder 6)
                - Memoranda and orders, 1919
              - Representatives abroad, 1919. (see also Siberia/Representatives abroad)
                - February-July (Folder 9)
                - August-December (Folder 10)
            - Representatives abroad, 1920 (Folder 11)
          - South. (see also Siberia/Omsk Government)
            - 1919
              - General (Folder 12)
              - Representatives abroad (Box 19, Folder 1)
                Available on microfilm reel 19
            - 1919-1920 (Folder 2)
            - 1920
              - General (Folder 3)
              - Representatives abroad
                - General (Folder 4)
                - Rules and regulations (Folder 5)
        - Supplies from abroad
          - General
            - 1918
              - January-August (Folder 6)
              - July-October (Folder 7)
                Available on microfilm reel 20
            - 1918-1919 (Folder 8)
            - 1919
              - January-October (Folder 9)
              - February-December (Box 20, Folder 1)
              - April-November (Folder 2)
              - May-December (Folder 3)
              - July-August (Folder 4)
                Available on microfilm reel 21
            - 1919-1920 (Folder 5-6)
            - 1921? (Folder 7)
          - North and North-West (Box 21)
            - General
              - 1919 (Folder 1)
              - 1920 (Folder 2)
            - Murmansk railroad (Folder 3)
            - North-West (Folder 4)
          - Russian cooperative organizations (Folder 5)
          - Siberia. (see also Subject File/ Germonius, Eduard)
            - 1919
              - January-July (Folder 6)
              - April-December (Folder 7)
                Available on microfilm reel 22
            - 1920 (Folder 8)
          - South. (see also Subject File/ Commercial products/1921; Subject File/Germonius, Eduard)
            - 1919 (Folder 9)
            - 1920 (Folder 10)
      - Nationality question (Box 22)
        - Baltic region
          - 1919 (Folder 1)
          - 1920 (Folder 2)
          - 1921 (Folder 3)
        - Bessarabia, Moldavia, Rumania, and Bukovina
          - n.d. (Folder 4)
            Available on microfilm reel 23
          - 1919 (Folder 5)
          - 1920 (Folder 6)
          - 1921 (Folder 7)
        - Bukovina--see Bessarabia/n.d.
        - Caucasus region
          - 1919 (Folder 8)
          - 1920 (Folder 9)
        - Finland (Folder 10)
        - Galicia
          - 1919 (Folder 11)
          - 1919-1920 (Folder 12)
          - 1920 (Box 23, Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 24
          - 1920-1921 (Folder 2)
        - Moldavia--see Bessarabia
        - Poland. (see also Galicia)
          - 1919 (Folder 3)
          - 1920 (Folder 4)
          - 1921 (Folder 5)
        - Rumania--see Bessarabia
        - Ukraine
          - 1919 (Folder 6)
          - 1920 (Folder 7)
      - Prisons and concentration camps--see Secret police; and Subject File/Russian intelligence service/1922/Russian Military Agent in Czechoslovakia
      - Secret police
        - "Krasnaia kniga VChK," Moscow, 1920. Type- written copy
          - Introduction (Folder 8)
          - Chapter 1 (Box 24, Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 25
          - Chapter 2 (Folder 2)
          - Chapter 3 (Folder 3)
        - Terror (Folder 4)
  - Russian church. (see also Refugees, Russian/China and Russia/Revolution, 1917-1922/Nationality question/ Galicia)
    - 1918 (Folder 5)
    - 1918-1919 (Folder 6)
      Available on microfilm reel 26
    - 1919 (Folder 7)
    - 1919-1920 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1920 (Folder 2)
    - 1921
      - January-October (Folder 3)
      - January-November (Folder 4)
    - 1922 (Folder 5)
      Available on microfilm reel 27
  - Russian Government Committee, London
    - 1915-1916 (Folder 6)
    - 1916 (Folder 7)
  - Russian Government Purchasing Commission. Speeches (Folder 8)
  - Russian Information Bureau, New York
    - Budget, 1921-1922 (Folder 9)
    - Russia/Revolution, 1917-1921 -- practical politics and war news. Telegrams (Box 26)
      - 1919
        - March-May (Folder 1)
        - May-July (Folder 2)
        - August-December (Folder 3)
          Available on microfilm reel 28
      - 1920 (Folder 4)
    - United States -- practical politics, 1919 (Folder 5)
  - Russian intelligence service. (see also Subagencies/ Consulates/Left wing movements in North America)
    - 1915 (Folder 6)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 7)
    - 1921 (Folder 8)
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 9)
    - 1922
      - General (Folder 10)
      - Russian Military Agent in Czechoslovakia (Folder 11)
  - Russian missions and legations (Box 27)
    - 1917-1918 (Folder 1)
    - 1918 (Folder 2)
      Available on microfilm reel 29
    - 1919 (Folder 3)
    - 1919-1920 (Folder 4-5)
    - 1919-1922 (Folder 6)
    - 1920
      - General (Folder 7)
      - Circular letters (Folder 8)
      - Orders (Folder 9)
    - 1920
      - General (Folder 10)
      - Reports (Folder 11)
        Available on microfilm reel 30
    - 1921 (Box 28)
      - January-November (Folder 1)
      - March-June (Folder 2)
      - September (Folder 3)
    - 1921-1922
      - General (Folder 4)
      - Correspondence (Folder 5)
  - Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic--see Russia
  - Russian Union of Zemstvos, Moscow, 1916. Report of the union's activities during the European War,1914-1918, with introduction by Prince G. E. L'vov (Folder 6)
  - Russian Volunteer Fleet
    - 1918
      - January-March (Folder 7)
      - April (Folder 8)
        Available on microfilm reel 31
      - June-December (Folder 9)
    - 1919 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - 1920 (Folder 2-3)
    - 1921
      - January-August (Folder 4)
        Available on microfilm reel 32
      - August-December (Folder 5)
    - 1922 (Folder 6)
  - Semenov, Grigorii, 1922. (see also Borah, William; and Russia/Revolution, 1917-1921/Counterrevolutionary movements/Governments and politics/Far East and Siberia) (Box 30)
    - March-May (Folder 1)
    - April-June (Folder 2)
  - Slavs (Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, Yugoslavia)
    - 1919 (Folder 3)
    - 1920 (Folder 4)
  - Subagencies
    - General (Folder 5)
    - Artillery Commission
      - General
        - Financial records (Folder 6)
          Available on microfilm reel 33
        - Reports (Folder 7)
      - Japanese military mission (Folder 8)
      - Main Artillery Administration, Petrograd (Folder 9)
    - Central Military Industrial Committee
      - 1918 (Folder 10)
      - 1919 (Folder 11)
      - 1920 (Folder 12)
    - Consulates
      - General
        - 1915 (Folder 13)
        - 1917-1918 (Folder 14)
        - 1919
          - March-August (Folder 15)
          - May-October (Folder 16)
        - 1920 (Box 31)
          - March-June (Folder 1)
          - April-October (Folder 2)
      - Chicago (Folder 3)
      - Left wing movements in North America
        - May-July (Folder 4)
          Available on microfilm reel 34
        - July-August (Folder 5)
        - September-November (Folder 6)
      - New York
        - General (Folder 7)
        - Strutsinskii, Nikolai
          - Correspondence (Folder 8-9)
          - Financial records (Folder 10)
            Available on microfilm reel 35
      - Pittsburgh (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - San Francisco
        - General
          - 1915 (Folder 2)
          - 1918
            - April-October (Folder 3)
            - November-December (Folder 4)
          - 1919
            - January-March (Folder 5)
            - April-December (Folder 6)
            - July-August (Folder 7)
              Available on microfilm reel 36
          - 1919-1920 (Folder 8)
          - 1920 (Folder 9)
          - 1921 (Folder 10)
        - Far East (Box 33)
          - Clippings
            - 1918-1919 (Folder 1)
            - 1920 (Folder 2)
            - 1921 (Folder 3)
          - Reports, 1920
            - January-June (Folder 4)
            - July-August (Folder 5)
            - August (Folder 6)
              Available on microfilm reel 37
            - September-October
              - Issues 1-4 (Folder 7)
              - Issues 5-7 (Box 34, Folder 1)
        - Far East, India, Persia (Folder 2)
        - India--see Far East, India, Persia
        - Persia--see Far East, India, Persia
      - Savings banks. (see also Subagencies/Financial Agent/1919)
        - General
          - Correspondence (Folder 3)
          - Historical reviews (Folder 4)
          - Reports (Folder 5)
        - Chicago
          - 1917-1918 (Folder 6)
          - 1918-1919 (Folder 7)
        - Montreal
          - General
            - 1918 (Folder 8)
            - 1919 (Folder 9)
              Available on microfilm reel 38
          - Correspondence, 1918
            - May-August (Folder 10)
            - September-November (Box 35, Folder 1)
          - Registers, 1917
            - June-September (Folder 2)
            - September-November (Folder 3)
              Available on microfilm reel 39
        - New York
          - 1918
            - Novitskii, Vladimir (Folder 4)
            - Uget, Sergei (Folder 5)
          - 1918-1919 (Folder 6)
        - Pittsburgh
          - 1917-1918 (Folder 7)
          - 1918-1919 (Folder 8)
        - San Francisco
          - 1918 (Folder 9)
          - 1918-1919 (Folder 10)
            Available on microfilm reel 40
        - Seattle (Box 36)
          - 1918 (Folder 1)
          - 1918-1919 (Folder 2)
      - Seattle (Folder 3)
    - Division of Supplies. (see also Subject File/Russian Volunteer Fleet/1918, June-December and also 1919 and 1920)
      - General Chancery
        - General (Folder 4)
        - Orders (Folder 5)
      - General Section
        - General
          - 1919 (Folder 6)
          - 1920 (Folder 7)
        - Orders
          - 1919 (Folder 8)
          - 1920 (Folder 9)
      - Financial Section
        - 1919
          - January-December (Folder 10)
            Available on microfilm reel 41
          - May-July (Folder 11)
          - July-September (Folder 12)
          - September-December (Box 37, Folder 1)
        - 1919-1920 (Folder 2)
          Available on microfilm reel 42
      - Mission of Ways of Communication, 1918
        - June (Folder 3)
        - June-September (Folder 4)
    - Extraordinary Mission, 1917 (Folder 5)
    - Financial Agent. (see also Subject File/Russian Volunteer Fleet/1921 and 1922)
      - 1919 (Folder 6)
      - 1920
        - General
          - January-August (Folder 7)
          - March-December (Folder 8)
            Available on microfilm reel 43
          - September-December (Box 38, Folder 1)
          - November-December (Folder 2)
        - Ter-Asaturov, Dmitrii. (see also Subject File/Financial Agent/1919) (Folder 3)
      - 1921
        - January-August (Folder 4)
        - March-May (Folder 5)
          Available on microfilm reel 44
        - March-November (Folder 6)
        - July-November (Folder 7)
      - 1921-1922 (Folder 8)
      - 1922 (Box 39)
        - January-May (Folder 1)
        - January-June (Folder 2)
    - Naval Agent (Folder 3)
    - Petrograd Zemstvos and Cities Regional Committee for Army Supplies
      - Financial records
        - Cash book (Folder 4)
          Available on microfilm reel 45
        - Report (Folder 5)
      - Minutes of board sessions (Folder 6)
    - Russian State Control
      - 1919 (Folder 7)
      - 1920 (Folder 8)
      - 1921 (Folder 9)